Guide to the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 2090 Records WAG.120
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 2090 Records
1881, 1917-1987
WAG.120
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
7.25 linear feet in 7 record cartons and 3 folders.
One of the older locals of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America in New York, Local 2090 was a cabinet makers local with a long German-socialist tradition. It was under left-wing leadership during the early-1930s. At the General Convention of 1936, Local 2090 led a campaign in opposition to amendments specifically directed at the Communist Party, which resulted in the revocation of its charter and a court case. The collection consists of the records of Local 2090 and other locals, possibly predecessors and successors, including Locals 1164, 2155, 2020, and 246. Materials include ledger books, minutes, contracts, correspondence, membership cards, legal documents, printed ephemera, and photographs, dating from 1881 to 1987.
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 1164.
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 2020.
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 2090.
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 2155.
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 246.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Historical/Biographical Note
One of the older locals of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America in New York, Local 2090 was a cabinet makers local with a long German-socialist tradition. It was under left-wing leadership during the early-1930s. At the General Convention of 1936, Local 2090 led a campaign in opposition to amendments specifically directed at the Communist Party. In early 1938, the local published and widely circulated a pamphlet stating their case, and its charter was subsequently revoked on grounds that the local's activity violated one of the new amendments. Local 2090 took the case to the civil courts, in Carpenters Union Local 2090 vs. Hutcheson, and were ultimately victorious. The legal process took several years, during which time the local's membership steadily decreased. In 1944 it was disbanded and replaced by Local 2155. Local 1164 was also under left-wing leadership in the early 1930s.
Sources:
Attie, Jeanie and Allen Steinberg. "Carpenters - New York State 100 Years of Progress: A History of the New York State Council of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America 1881-1981." New York State Council United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, 1982.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of the records of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 2090 and other locals, possibly predecessors and successors, including Locals 1164, 2155, 2020, and 246. Materials include ledger books, minutes, dues books, contracts, correspondence, membership cards, legal documents, printed ephemera, and photographs, dating from 1881 to 1987. Also includes legal materials, resolutions, circulars and other printed ephemera from the court case Carpenters Local Union No. 2090 vs. Hutcheson, in which Local 2090 succesfully challenged the revocation of its charter by the General Executive Board of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America.
Immediate Source fo Acquisition
The United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 2090 sent a gift of their records in 2000. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1999.016 and 1999.017.
Building trades |x Employees |x Labor Unions |z United States.; Building trades |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1942-1942 (Box 1)
- Local 1164: Minutes - Executive Board, 1927-1963 (Box 1)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1926-1927 (Box 1)
- Local 1164: Minutes, 1927-1932 (Box 1)
- Local 1164: Minutes, 1952-1961 (Box 1)
- Local 1164: Minutes, 1937-1941 (Box 1)
- Local 1164: Minutes, 1932-1936 (Box 1)
- Local 1164: Minutes, 1923-1926 (Box 1)
- Local 1164: Minutes, 1917-1923 (Box 1)
- Local 1164: Minutes, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1932-1933 (Box 2)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1938-1939 (Box 2)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1924-1925 (Box 2)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1930-1931 (Box 2)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1943-1949 (Box 3)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1949-1961 (Box 3)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1930-1931 (Box 3)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1961-1963 (Box 3)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1949-1959 (Box 3)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1928-1929 (Box 4)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1926-1927 (Box 4)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1945-1947 (Box 5)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1942-1943 (Box 5)
- Local 1164: Ledger Book, 1977-1987 (Box 5)
- Local 2155: Photos, undated (Box A004)
- Local 2020: Photos, undated (Box 5)
- Local 246: Photos, undated (Box A004)
- Local 2090: Photographs, undated (Box A004)
- Local 2090: New York Supreme Court of Appeals, 1938 (Box 6)
- Local 2090: Transcripts, 1938 (Box 6)
- Local 2090: Minutes, 1928-1930 (Box 6)
- Local 2090: Minutes, 1918-1921 (Box 6)
- Local 2090: Minutes, 1925-1927 (Box 6)
- Local 2090: Minutes, 1935-1936 (Box 6)
- Local 2090: Minutes, 1938-1944 (Box 6)
- Local 2090: Minutes, 1930-1933 (Box 6)
- Local 2090: Minutes, 1921-1925 (Box 6)
- Local 2090: Minutes, 1930-1933 (Box 7)
- Local 2090: Dues Books from Germany, undated (Box 7)
- Local 2090: Contracts, undated (Box 7)
- Local 2090: Correspondence, 1930s (Box 7)
- Local 2090: Membership Cards, 1881 (Box 7)
- Archived Website, Mar 20, 2009-ongoing
  Scope and Content Note
  The United Brotherhood of Carpenters Shop and Industrial Local 2790 was formed in August 2011, from the dissolution of the Architectural Woodworkers Local 2090 and Industrial Local 2870. UBC Local Union 2790 is a specialty trade union that represents carpenters, industrial shop workers, architectural woodworkers, millworkers, finish carpenters, wood finishers, cabinet installers, trim carpenters, architectural metal workers, and cabinetmakers throughout the five boroughs of New York City; as well as Long Island, New Jersey, and Westchester County. Local 2790 is part of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters & Joiners of America, and the New York City District Council of Carpenters. The website includes news listings, wages and benefits, event listings, images, and other reports.